Guide to the Laura (Riding) Jackson and Schuyler B. Jackson collection, 1924-1991
Jackson, Laura (Riding) and Schuyler B., 1924-1991
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Laura (Riding) Jackson and Schuyler B. Jackson collection, 1924-1991
4608
Laura (Riding) Jackson, 1901-
24.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, literary manuscripts, unpublished works, audio recording.
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Consists mainly of correspondence between Laura (Riding) Jackson and a substantial number of authors, critics, publishers and friends. The collection also gathers literary manuscripts, in particular revised drafts of book-length unpublished works, and notes and commentaries written by Laura (Riding) Jackson about her poetry and criticism. Includes an audio recording of (Riding) Jackson reading in New York City, 1984.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Born in New York City in 1901, Laura (Riding) Jackson occupies the American literary landscape of the Twentieth Century as a poet, critic, and author increasingly concerned with language "as the natural human truth-system." She is best known for her association with the Fugitives in the 1920s, her personal and literary partnership with Robert Graves between 1925 and 1938, and as editor of Epilogue. Yet, as a modernist poet, a critic whose work was at the base of the New Criticism, and in her editorial work, she engaged in a relentless dialogue with scores of poets, authors, and critics of the Twentieth Century, which she pursued until her death in 1991. The Laura (Riding) Jackson and Schuyler B. Jackson Collection fully documents the strength of her dedication to the search for the sources of meaning, as well as her appeal to those who worked with her.
CHRONOLOGY
1901 Born in New York City, the daughter of Nathaniel Reichenthal and Sadie Edersheim Reichenthal (Nathan's first wife was Laura Lorber, with whom he had a daughter, Isabel).
1918 Enrolls at Cornell University, which she attends for three years. Here she meets Esther (Polly) Antell, who will become a lifelong friend, and Louis Gottschalk, a history instructor.
1920 Louis Gottschalk and Laura Riding are married. In 1921 accompanies him first to Urbana, Illinois, then to Louisville, Kentucky, where he has teaching positions.
1923 Assumes the name Laura Riding Gottschalk. Her poems begin to appear in various magazines, including The Fugitive.
1924 The literary circle 'The Fugitives' awards her the Nashville Prize. In November, attends one of their meetings in Nashville.
1925 She and Louis Gottschalk are divorced. She moves to New York City where she becomes friends with the poet Hart Crane and various other American writers. Her first critical essay, "A Prophecy or a Plea," published in April. Robert Graves invites her to collaborate on a book about modern poetry. Sails for England at the end of the year.
1926 In January, accompanies Robert Graves and his wife Nancy Nicholson to Egypt, from which they return to England in July. Her first book of poems, The Close Chaplet, is published by Leonard and Virginia Woolf's Hogarth Press in England and by Adelphi in the United States.
1927 Her verse fantasy Voltaire (written 1921) is published by the Hogarth Press. Publishes, with Robert Graves, A Survey of Modernist Poetry. Founds the Seizin Press with Graves. Changes name, by deed poll, to Laura Riding.
1928 Some of her major critical works are published: Contemporaries and Snobs in February; Anarchism is Not Enough in May; A Pamphlet Against Anthologies, with Robert Graves, in July (all by Jonathan Cape). The Seizin Press publishes her collection of poems Love as Love, Death as Death. Publishes poems in various magazines, including transition. Meets Gertrude Stein during a visit to Paris.
1929 Attempts suicide on April 27. In October leaves London with Graves and moves to Deya, Mallorca, where they relocate the Seizin Press.
1930 Jonathan Cape publishes Poems: A Joking Word and Experts Are Puzzled; Nancy Cunard's Hours Press publishes Twenty Poems Less and Four Unposted Letters to Catherine; and Though Gently is published by the Seizin Press.
1930-1935 During her stay at Deya in the 1930s she is visited by a number of English and American friends including poets Norman Cameron and James Reeves, mathematician and writer Jacob Bronowski, filmmaker and artist Len Lye, artist John Aldridge, journalist and novelist Honor Wyatt, and T.S. Matthews, who will become managing editor of Time magazine. With Robert Graves founds Epilogue. Other collaborative projects include Life of the Dead (1933) illustrated by John Aldridge; and 14A (1934), written with George Ellidge.
1935 Progress of Stories is published by Constable/Seizin.
1936 After the start of the Spanish Civil War, Riding and Graves are forced to evacuate Deya with only one suitcase apiece; they relocate to London.
1937 A Trojan Ending is published by Constable/Seizin Press in England and Random House in the United States. Riding and Graves spend four months in Switzerland, working on various writing projects including their collected poems.
1938 Collected Poems is published by Cassell and Random House. With others, composes The Covenant of Literal Morality, and publishes The World and Ourselves and The Left Heresy in Literature and Life, whose first author is Harry Kemp. In June, settles in France with Graves, sharing a house with Beryl and Alan Hodge.
1939 In April, returns to the United States at the invitation of T.S. Matthews. Meets Schuyler B. Jackson. Lives of Wives is published by Cassell and Random House. Seizin Press terminated. Her relationship with Robert Graves ends. With Schuyler Jackson she resumes work on A Dictionary of Related Meanings, which she had started with Jacob Bronowski and continued with Robert Graves and Alan Hodge in the 1930s. Dent in England and Little, Brown in the United States contract to publish the work.
1941 Schuyler Jackson and Laura Riding are married; they settle near New Hope, Pennsylvania.
1942 "The Latest in Synonymy," by Schuyler and Laura Jackson, published in the Wilson Library Bulletin.
1943 Moves to Wabasso, Florida. New contracts for Dictionary signed with Little, Brown and Dent. Jacksons begin fruit shipping business while continuing to work on the Dictionary.
1946 Little, Brown cancels the contract for the book.
1950 Jacksons begin work on a new language project, which would become Rational Meaning: A New Foundation for the Definition of Words. Also continue work on Charles M. Doughty, which Schuyler Jackson had begun years earlier on his own. Terminate fruit shipping business in September, due to Schuyler's ill-health.
1955 Publishes, as Laura (Riding) Jackson, her first statement indicating her renunciation of poetry ("a cautious generalization") in Twentieth Century Authors: First Supplement.
1962 Reading of Laura Riding poems broadcast by BBC, prefaced by first statement of reasons for renunciation of poetry. "Introduction To A Broadcast" subsequently appeared in Chelsea magazine--the first of many periodical articles, on varied topics, published 1962-1991, and after.
1963 Reading of Four Unposted Letters to Catherine broadcast by BBC. First public use of the name Laura (Riding) Jackson in Civilta' delle Macchine (next in Chelsea, January 1964).
1967 Core-piece of The Telling published in Chelsea.
1968 Schuyler Jackson dies on July 4th.
1970 Faber and Faber publishes Selected Poems: In Five Sets in Great Britain (W.W. Norton &Co. publishes the book in the United States in 1973).
1971 Granted the Mark Rothko Appreciation Award.
1972 The Athlone Press of the University of London publishes The Telling in Great Britain, Harper & Row in the United States (1973). In January a reading of her poetry is recorded for Lamont Library, Harvard College.
1973 Recipient of a Guggenheim fellowship.
1976 Chelsea publishes a special issue (35) dedicated to Laura (Riding) Jackson, which collects many of her works of the 1970s.
1979 Recipient of a National Endowment for the Arts fellowship.
1980 The Poems of Laura Riding, a re-issue of the 1938 Collected Poems with appendices and a new introduction, published by Carcanet Press in Manchester, England, and Persea Books in New York. Targ Editions publishes Description of Life.
1981 Nominated by Danish poet Poul Borum for the Neustadt Prize.
1982 Carcanet and Dial Press republish Progress of Stories with other early stories, new preface, and other new material.
1983 Some Communications of Broad Reference published by Lord John Press, Northridge, California.
1984 Carcanet republishes A Trojan Ending with a new preface by Laura (Riding) Jackson. The book is translated into Spanish and appears as Final Troyano from Edhasa, Barcelona, in 1986.
1988 Carcanet republishes Lives of Wives.
1991 90th-birthday celebration published in Chelsea (USA) and PN Review (UK). Laura (Riding) Jackson is co-recipient, with Donald Justice, of the Bollingen Prize. She dies in Wabasso on September 2nd.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
The Laura (Riding) Jackson and Schuyler B. Jackson Collection spans the years 1924-1991 and occupies 24.2 cubic feet. It consists mainly of correspondence between Laura (Riding) Jackson and a substantial number of authors, critics, publishers, and friends. In her correspondence Laura (Riding) Jackson discusses her views on poetry and language and provides criticism of other writers' work. The correspondence includes letters to and from the literary circle of friends that Laura (Riding) Jackson established in England, in Deya, Mallorca, and in France during the 1930s, among them Jacob Bronowski, Tom Matthews, and Gertrude Stein. More recent correspondence, mainly from the 1960s to the 1980s, documents Laura (Riding) Jackson 's relationship with American and British writers and critics, and details the projects and literary concerns that occupied her until her death.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Jackson, Laura (Riding), 1901-; Jackson, Laura (Riding), 1901-; Graves, Robert.; Jackson, Schuyler B.
Subjects:
American literature--20th century.; Modernism (Literature).; American poetry--20th century.; Language and languages--Study and teaching.; Criticism--United States.; Criticism--Great Britain.; Authors, American.
Occupations:
Women authors--United States.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
Access Restrictions:
By appointment only. Researchers may view one folder at a time.
PROVENANCE
The provenance of the Laura (Riding) Jackson and Schuyler B. Jackson Collection is complex, the result of both gifts to and purchases by Cornell University. The Collection originated in 1965 when Mrs. Jackson decided to donate her papers to Cornell University, and began to send materials to the Department of Rare Books. She continued to do so until 1987. In addition, Mrs. Jackson bequeathed parts of the collection to Cornell University. Ms. Elizabeth Friedmann also donated materials given to her by Laura (Riding) Jackson which are included in the Laura (Riding) Jackson and Schuyler B. Jackson Collection. Other collections of letters written by Laura (Riding) Jackson were donated by certain of her correspondents or purchased by Cornell University. Several of these purchases and donations now constitute separate related collections. See Related Material.
RELATED MATERIAL
Related Cornell collections:
The Albert Burns, Robert Sproat, and Audrey Sproat Collection of Laura (Riding) Jackson Correspondence, # 6300
The Beryl Graves Collection of Laura (Riding) Jackson Letters, # 6301
The Warren Hope Collection of Laura (Riding) Jackson Letters, # 6302
The Griselda J. Ohannessian Collection of Laura (Riding) Jackson Letters, # 6303
The James Reeves - Laura (Riding) Jackson Correspondence, # 6304
The Dorothy Simmons Collection of Laura (Riding) Jackson Letters, # 6305
Other repositories in the United States holding Laura (Riding) Jackson materials:
Alderman Library, University of Virginia, Charlottesville
Amherst College Library
The Bancroft Library, University of California, Berkeley
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Yale University
Butler Library, Columbia University
Richard A. Gleeson Library, University of San Francisco
John Hay Library, Brown University
Jean and Alexander Heard Library, Vanderbilt University
Joint University Libraries, Nashville, Tennessee
Library of Congress (Manuscript Division)
Lilly Library, University of Indiana
Lockwood Memorial Library, State University of New York at Buffalo
McFarlin Library, University of Tulsa
McKeldin Library, University of Maryland
Delyte W. Morris Library, Southern Illinois University
Morris Library, Southern Illinois University
Mugar Memorial Library, Boston University
New York Public Library. Henry W. and Albert A. Berg Collection of English and American Literature
Northwestern University Library
Harry Ransom Humanities Research Center, University of Texas
Louis Round Wilson Library, University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill
Kenneth Spencer Research Library, University of Kansas Libraries
University of Chicago Library, Poetry magazine papers
University of Florida Libraries
Washington University at St. Louis
Other repositories outside the United States holding Laura (Riding) Jackson materials:
Cambridge University Library
Leicester University
University of Reading
University of Sussex Library
University of Victoria Library
COLLECTION ARRANGEMENT
The collection is organized into the following series: Autobiographical Materials, Diaries, Correspondence, Literary Manuscripts, Broadcasts, Recordings and Readings, Professional Activities, Other Activities, Writings about Laura (Riding) Jackson, Writings by Others, Photographs, and Ephemera.
Autobiographical Materials span the years 1938-1977. Arranged chronologically, they consist mainly of pieces written for periodicals, entries for biographical dictionaries, and personal notes and commentaries.
Diaries are subdivided into the Laura (Riding) Jackson Diaries (1960-1980), and Schuyler B. Jackson Diaries (1964-1968). They are arranged and stored by format, rather than by date, because they were entered on notepads of greatly varying sizes. Thus the researcher needs to scan the whole list when looking for specific dates.
Correspondence spans the years 1926-1990. The letters are organized in the following three subseries: Laura (Riding) Jackson Correspondence, Schuyler B. Jackson Correspondence, and Formerly Restricted Correspondence (all access restrictions were lifted in 2016); Correspondence that was formerly restricted fell into three categories: Category (B) including:
1) Correspondence to and from Sonia Raiziss
2) Correspondence to and from the Guggenheim Foundation after 1975
3) Correspondence to and from Mrs. E. M. (Sally) Chilver
4) Correspondence to and from James Mathias after 1975
6) Correspondence to and from Mark Jacobs
7) Correspondence to and from John Nolan
8) Correspondence to and from Robert Nye, Alan Clark, Theodore Wilentz, Joan Wilentz, Elizabeth Friedmann, William Harmon, James Tyler
Category (C) They are:
1) Correspondence to and from any of the four children of Schuyler B. Jackson, namely Benjamin Schuyler Jackson, Maria Jackson Parker, Griselda Jackson Ohannessian, and Katharine Jackson McCagg
2) Correspondence to and from Katharine Townsend Jackson
3) Correspondence to and from Grace Friedberg
4) Correspondence to and from Eric and Margaret (Peggy) Rideal and Peter and Mary Oliver
5) Correspondence to and from Mrs. Jackson's brother, Robert Reichenthal (aka Robert Ritchey)
6) Correspondence to and from Mrs. Jackson's sister, Isabel Mayers, and her nephew, Richard Mayers
7) Diaries of Schuyler B. Jackson and Laura (Riding) Jackson
Category (D):
1) A group of letters, from Laura (Riding) Jackson to Joyce Wexler 2) Correspondence to and from Gertrude Stein
Each subseries is arranged into incoming and outgoing correspondence. The incoming correspondence is arranged in alphabetical order by name of correspondent, with the unidentified senders placed at the beginning of the subseries; the outgoing correspondence is in chronological order, with the undated letters at the beginning of the subseries. However, there are two exceptions. Some materials in the incoming correspondence have been kept in thematic order, as Laura (Riding) Jackson arranged them. These are the letters relating to the fruit shipping business and the incoming selected Christmas messages. The formerly restricted correspondence for each individual is housed in separate boxes, the materials being arranged into incoming and outgoing correspondence. The letters of Theodore Wilentz to and from Laura (Riding) Jackson are interfiled with those of his wife Joan.
Literary manuscripts span the years 1926-1991. The series includes works by both Laura (Riding) Jackson and Schuyler B. Jackson, with whom she worked on The Dictionary of Related Meanings and Rational Meaning. The materials are subdivided into two categories, published and unpublished manuscripts and are further subdivided by genre: Major works, Poems, Essays and commentaries, and Letters to editors. All materials are arranged in chronological order when dated, otherwise in alphabetical order. The Major Works section includes book-length projects of criticism, collaborations, translations, and pamphlets individually published; Essays and commentaries includes works published as parts of other works, such as contributions to periodicals or to collections of essays, and a variety of notes and commentaries on Laura (Riding) Jackson 's works, on others' works, and on poetry and language in general. Her notes about her own works written after publication are placed in the Unpublished works section, unless the notes themselves were published. Letters to editors of journals and magazines, written in response to book reviews of Laura (Riding) Jackson 's works, are placed among the literary manuscripts rather than in the correspondence series, as they are often literary essays in their own right.
The Major Works subdivision in the Unpublished Works section contains a variety of manuscript and typescript drafts, notes, and background materials that are sporadically dated. They have been arranged in alphabetical order by title, then within each title in the following order: background materials, manuscript drafts, typescript drafts, notes and commentaries.
Materials in the Broadcasts, Recordings, and Readings series span the years 1963-1972 and are arranged in chronological order. They include the text of the Preface of Four Unposted Letters to Catherine written in 1963 for a reading aired by BBC on July 15 and 16, 1963, revised for the occasion; notes and transcripts of a poetry reading recorded at Lamont Library, Harvard College, in January 1972; and corrections for a recording made at the Library of Congress.
Materials in the Professional Activities series span the years 1936-1976. They are arranged chronologically and include a contract stipulated by the Seizin Press and a grant application from Laura (Riding) Jackson to the Guggenheim Foundation.
Materials in the Other Activities series span the years 1973-1978 and consist of documents and correspondence relating to Mrs. Jackson's involvement in a dispute over a development project in Wabasso, Florida, where she resided.
Materials in the Writings about Laura (Riding) Jackson series span the years 1932-1990 and are subdivided into the following two sections: Biographical Pieces and Critical Reception of Laura (Riding) Jackson's Works. The latter section includes book reviews and critical essays, in addition to entries in reference works and anthologies. The book reviews are listed in chronological order of appearance in periodicals, the essays in the chronological order of publication of the works in which they are contained.
Materials in the Writings by Others series span the years 1926-1981 and include clippings from reviews and articles on language, literature, and a variety of other subjects, which Laura (Riding) Jackson found of interest and collected. They are listed in chronological order of appearance.
The Photographs series consists of fifteen black and white photographs, which span the 1920s to the 1980s. They include photographs of paintings of Laura (Riding) Jackson.
The Memorabilia series includes a number of legal documents.
SERIES LIST
Series I. Autobiographical material
Box 1
Series II. Diaries
a) Laura (Riding) Jackson Diaries
Boxes 2-9
b) Schuyler B. Jackson Diaries
Boxes 10-11
Series III. Correspondence
A) Laura (Riding) Jackson
Boxes 12-47
Incoming
Outgoing
B) Schuyler B. Jackson
Box 48
Incoming
Outgoing
C) Formerly Restricted Correspondence
Boxes 49-75
Series IV. Literary Manuscripts
Published
Boxes 76-84 (part)
Major Works
Poems
Essays and Articles
Letters to editors
Editorial Activities
Unpublished Works
Boxes 84 (part)-96
Book-Length Projects
Poems
Short Essays and Notes
Letters to editors
Editorial Activities
Series V. Broadcasts, Recordings, and Readings
Box 97 (part)
Series VI. Professional activities
Box 97 (part)
Series VII. Other Activities
The Wabasso Development Project
Box 97 (part)-98
Series VIII. Writings about Laura (Riding ) Jackson and Schuyler Benjamin Jackson
Box 99 (part)
Series IX. Writings by others
Box 99 (part)-100
Series X. Photographs
Box 101 (part)
Series XI. Memorabilia
Box 101 (end)
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Autobiographical material
  - "Autobiographical" ms. 6pp.[n.d.]; ms. 4pp.[n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "An Autobiographical Summary" ts. 52pp.[n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "An Autobiographical Summary" ts. 28pp.[n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - "Biographical material" (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Hart Crane, July 20, 1964 letter to Robert Nye..." ms. 1p.; [price list from catalog?] ms. 1p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [on "Maria's Tom"] Aug. 31, 1971 ms. 1p. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "When you are given an allowance..." [by SBJ?] ms. 3pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "How to make the best use of this box" ts. 2pp. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - [On Robert Graves] ms. 8 pp.; ts. 2pp. [n.d.] (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [pieces for periodicals and reference works] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "I was born in New York City ..." [ autobiographical piece for Contemporary Authors 1938.] ts. 3pp. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - "Contributor note for MS Magazine" ts. 1p. n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - [Materials and corrections for Norton Anthology] ms. 4pp.; ts. 2pp.; ms. 5pp. (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - [note on an issue of Modern Language Quarterly and True West] ts. 1p. photocopy; issue of the magazine (February 1973) (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - [On Rebecca West] ms. 1p.; ms. 8pp. October 1977 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Personal notes and memoranda in which she identifies her correspondents for the Department of Rare Books at Cornell University between 1967 and 1985] (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Series II. Diaries
  - A) Laura (Riding) Jackson Diaries
    - [Misc. incomplete accounts and tax records, 1965-1968] (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Diary, Oct. 11-Dec. 31, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Travel Diary, July 6-Oct. 4, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Diary, Oct. 31, 1961-Jan. 27, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Diary, Feb. 3-June 31, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Diary, July 1-Dec. 31, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Diary, Jan. 1-May 31, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Diary, June 1-Dec. 31, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Diary, Aug. 8, Nov. 26, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Diary, Jan. 1-May 31, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Diary, June 1-Dec. 31, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Travel Diary, Sept. 3-Oct. 25, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Diary, Jan. 1-May 31, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Diary, June 1-Dec. 31, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Travel Diary, Aug. 2-Sept. 20, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Diary, Jan, 1-June 30, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Diary, July 1-Dec. 31, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Diary, Jan. 1-Apr. 30, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Diary, May 1-Dec. 31, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Diary, Jan. 1-Feb. 28, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Diary, Mar. 1-Apr. 30, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)